# 褪下来了
It’s peeled off.
# 好
Good.
# 再冲一下
Wash it one more time.
# 更脆
Crispier.
# 好嘞
Excellent.
# 鱼香脆皮虾
Fish-flavored crispy shrimps.
# 今天咱做一个与众不同的酥皮虾
Today we are bringing a unique recipe of crispy shrimps.
# 一个是它的改刀方式
One thing unique is the cutting
# 再一个它的口味
Another is its taste.
# 这个一个是小焦来了
Here is Xiao Jiao.
# 一个是你向来都是与众不同是吧
You have always been unique, right?
# 关键我来师兄必须做大菜
The key point is that my big bro has to cook serious dishes when I come here.
# 小菜我看不上他呀
Small dishes I can do better.
# 诶 什么虾
What type of shrimp is it?
# 海白虾
White shrimp.
# 虾头剪掉 虾腿剪掉
Cut off the head and legs.
# 这个是关键
This is the crucial part.
# 我腹部开刀
Cut along the belly.
# 他这样那皮就整个褪下来了
In this way the shell could be peeled off thoroughly.
# 就跟虾蜕皮似的
It’s like the moulting of shrimps themselves.
# 腹开啊 两边腹开
Expose the belly, cut the edges.
# 这菜很快啊
It’s a quick dish.
# 褪下来了好
Peeled off, good.
# 你看三叔揣着兜 检验
Look at San Shu! Hands in his pocket, checking out right now. Haha!
# 这叫检阅
It’s called inspection.
# 虾线必须挑掉
Sand vein must be removed.
# 摘掉
Done.
# 咱们是用几头虾
How big are the shrimps?
# 八个头
Eight shrimps per 500g.
# 八个头350克大概多少钱
How much is it for 350g?
# 成本
Cost?
# 40来块钱
40 RMB, a bit more.
# 40多块钱在家做一大菜
You can cook a serious dish at home with this 40 RMB.
# 值 很值
Worth it! Totally worth it!
# 咱把这个虾给他冲白了
Wash the shrimps until they turn white.
# 把血沫子都给它冲走
Wash out all of the scums.
# 通过凉水这一激 它成型了
Use the cold water to contract the meat. It has gone firm now.
# 咱把虾给它沾一下
Let’s get rid of excess water with a towel.
# 再给它腌一下
And marinate the shrimps.
# 稍微搁点盐
A little bit salt.
# 好料酒（黄酒）来点
A little bit rice wine.
# 少搁点葱姜
Less scallion and ginger.
# 腌多长时间啊
How long does it take?
# 腌 大概个10来分钟
Marinate for a bit more than 10 minutes.
# 好
Ok.
# 咱就给他蘸一下粉子
Let's dredge the shrimps in starch.
# 这是玉米淀粉
This is corn starch.
# 蘸这虾的时候
When dredging the shrimp
# 千万不能蘸着虾皮
Make sure the shell doesn't touch the starch
# 诶 OK
Well, ok.
# 这要待会炸吧
Is it supposed to be fried later?
# 炸完以后它不打卷吗
Aren’t they gonna curl up after fried?
# 要它打卷 就让他打卷
We need them to curl up, so let 'em be.
# 对 卷起来
Yes, curl up.
# 烧油的同时
While the oil is heating up,
# 来 先把这鱼香汁给调出来
Let’s make this fish-flavored sauce at the same time.
# 绵白糖 三勺
Three spoonful of white sugar
# 醋和糖的比例1：1
The ratio of vinegar to sugar is 1:1
# 黄酒
Yellow rice wine
# 少来点酱油
Soy sauce, not too much.
# 少来 好 调色
A little bit, good, for coloring.
# 少来点胡椒粉
A little bit of pepper.
# 加点水
Add some water.
# 好嘞
Great.
# 这个鱼香口刚才还说了半天
We have been talking about this “fish-flavored taste” for a while.
# 到底是什么口
So what is it exactly?
# 鱼香口应该是酸甜咸鲜
A fish-flavored taste should include acidity, sweetness, saltiness, and umami.
# 微辣
A little spicy?
# 但是在四川什么味儿
How does it taste in Sichuan cuisine?
# 咸在前 咸甜酸辣香
Saltiness ranks the first, followed by sweetness, acidity, spiciness and aroma.
# 有麻味吗
Any numbness?
# 没有
No.
# 刨坑
A trap question.
# 这个是坚决没有
Hahhah definitely not!
# 老同志脑瓜反应快
The senior got a quick reflex!
# 所以说三叔你看任何菜都涉及到改良
So, San Shu, here it is, any recipe could be improved and adapted.
# 有好多网友朋友们一说
Many friends would call a recipe “authentic”
# 正宗正宗
authentic, authentic.
# 什么叫正宗
What is “authentic”?
# 三叔我是这么觉得
I think it this way, San Shu
# 你只要吃好吃 吃满意
As long as it satisfies your taste,
# 这就叫正宗
It could be called “Authentic”.
# 适合你的口味就叫正宗
“Authentic taste” is the taste that suits you.
# 没错
Exactly.
# 真正把川菜拿过来
If I brought you a local Sichuan dish here,
# 你其实不一定能吃
You might not be used to it.
# 我老饭骨其实也是秉承这种家庭口味
We Lao Fan Gu insist on the family taste meals.
# 然后让你吃着很满意的口味
And create tastes that satisfy your tastebuds
# 让你自己能操作的口味来做咱们
Our cooking instruction mainly focuses on deliciousness
# 在自己家里边能做的美食
that can be easily replicated at home
# 对吧
Right?
# 所以说别拿正宗说事
So forget about being authentic.
# 来先把虾头炸一下
Let’s fry shrimps’ heads first.
# 注意啊 别烫着
Be cautious, don’t burn yourself.
# 得睡醒了
Make sure you are awake.
# 你魏兄是
Your brother, Wei,
# OK
Ok
# 给自己定为梦中人
He identifies himself as a man living in dreams.
# 漂亮啊 漂亮吧
It looks wonderful, isn’t it?
# 这就OK了
And now it’s done.
# 对
Yes.
# 要的脆劲儿
Crispiness is what we need.
# 拿大漏勺
Take a large slotted spoon.
# 油温正好啊 招呼
The oil temperature is perfect. Let’s do it.
# 一个一个的下
We cook them one by one?
# 三个一块下
Three at a time.
# 这虾出来绝对脆
These shrimps are definitely gonna be crispy!
# 你听这声儿
You can hear this sound.
# 啪啪
piapiapia
# 这油温有200度 九成油温
The temperature of oil seems to around 200 Celsius degree, 90% of the maximum temp.
# 没有九成油温
Less than 90%.
# 这个也就是七成 七到八成
It’s only around 70% or 80%
# 九成油温快冒烟了
Oil would have been smoking if it’s at 90%
# 看看
Look at it.
# 还是小焦
Still count on Xiao Jiao.
# 所以三叔说三七二百一么
So as San Shu said, 70% heat is 210 degrees Celsius.
# 这个脆皮虾关键皮得脆
The key point of this “Crispy shrimps” is its crispness.
# 再复炸一下
Let’s fry one more time.
# 网友朋友们 看看啊
Hey my friends, look at it.
# 这个油温高 看看虾皮是透的
The shell looks transparent as the oil temperature is high.
# 如果油温低 坏了
If the oil temperature is low, it will go bad,
# 乌哒哒
Looks cloudy.
# 再冲一下 更脆
Let’s fry one more time, make it crispier!
# 好嘞
Great!
# 齐活
Perfect!
# 关键你看没有网友们 必须得洗干净了
Hey my friends, did you notice that? The key point is to wash the shrimps until they are absolutely clean.
# 看见没有 多亮
Look, how bright it is!
# 里外晶莹剔透
Clear like crystal both inside and outside.
# 跟穿着一裙子似的
Look like a wonderful dress on the shrimp.
# 没错
Exactly.
# 油倒走
Get rid of the oil.
# 师兄您今儿选择这是什么虾啊
Bro what shrimps did you use today?
# 泰国的 海白虾
White shrimps, from Thailand.
# 而且得用皮儿薄的
And we selected those with thin shells.
# 其实我觉着一通百通
In fact, I think if you know the key you will know all.
# 有什么拿什么
You can cook whatever in your hands.
# 做出来按这种手法都好看
Followed this recipe, they are all gonna be excellent.
# 对
Yes.
# 现在开始调汁儿
Now we prepare the sauce.
# 加点儿淀粉
Add a bit starch.
# 生粉
Cornstarch.
# 勾芡
Thickening.
# 水淀粉
Slurry
# 咱们锅得用凉油了 不能用热油了
Now we have to use cooled oil, instead of hot oil.
# 哎 热锅凉油
Check out, hot wok with cool oil.
# 豆瓣酱得剁一下
We mince the doubanjiang (aka fermented broad bean paste).
# 泡椒也得剁一下
Pickled peppers need to be minced as well.
# 不剁一下颗粒太粗糙
Otherwise the particles would be too rough.
# 这二合酱啊
This is a bi-mixed sauce.
# 这个关键点是必须得炒透了
The key point is to stir fry those substances until well-done.
# 炒酥
All the way until crispy.
# 香油
Sesame oil.
# 加点姜末 先放姜末
Add some minced ginger first.
# 葱花
Chopped scallions.
# 蒜蓉
Minced garlic
# 因为川菜小料必须得重
Sichuan cuisine is heavy on the aromatics
# 小料太重鱼香味才能出得来
The fish-flavored taste will not come through without these strong aromatics
# 嘿 出来了香味
Hey, the tasty flavor comes out.
# 料酒（黄酒）
Rice wine.
# 这汁儿这么混呢
Why does the sauce look muddy?
# 传统手法 加芡儿了
Traditional method, thickening.
# 搅起来待会打熟了它就不混了
Keep stirring. The mixed sauce will go clear after well cooked.
# 顺一个方向转 不能胡搅和
Stir the sauce along one direction. Don’t stir randomly.
# 亮油
Put on some oil.
# 嘿 正好热油 热油最亮
Hey, exactly what we need, hot oil looks the brightest!
# 少来点葱花
Garnish with some chopped scallion.
# 咱把虾摆一下
Now we present the plate.
# 好
Ok
# 生活需要仪式感
An ordinary life needs a sense of ritual.
# 需要讲究点
Need a right amount of selectiveness.
# 讲究点
Yep, selectiveness.
# 皮酥肉嫩
Tender shrimps with crispy shell.
# 鱼香脆皮虾
Fish-flavored crispy shrimps.
# 嘿 小汁黏度合适 黏黏的
Hey, the thickness of the sauce is perfect. It’s sticky.
# 诶 小魏 这汁儿盛碗里什么意思
Hey Wei, how come the sauce is inside the bowl?
# 盛碗里就是蘸汁吃
You dip the shrimp in the sauce.
# 这样它不会破坏它的形状
This way the shrimp will keep the shape.
# 不会破坏它的脆度
And preserve its crispiness.
# 但是也不影响它的口味
And it won’t affect the taste.
# 好 吃起来
Wonderful, let’s eat!
# 我先蘸一下看看
I try it with the sauce first.
# 嗯 听着这声到脆嘿
Yummmm, you can tell how crispy it is by the sound!
# 都20分钟了
After 20 minutes,
# 还这么脆
It’s still very crispy.
# 我尝尝 来来 尝尝
I ll have some too.
# 皮也蘸点啊
Get some sauce on the shell as well.
# 汁兜多点
To carry more sauce.
# 我也来一个
I ll have one too.
# 嘿 你听这声
Hey check out the sound.
# 声音
The sound.
# 倍儿脆啊
Extremely crispy.
# 其实我还是讲究味道
In fact, I valued the taste of food much.
# 这鱼香汁熬得真好 是吧
This fish-flavored sauce is so delicious! Right?
# 这个虾的形式也好
The shape of the shrimps is delicate as well.
# 其实挺简单的
In fact, it’s not very hard.
# 对
Yep
# 不要觉得复杂
Don’t consider it too complicated.
# 那么还是在家亲手的操作操作
So, you’d better practice it at home. Give it a try.
# import ending.srt 00:06:31,850